<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>The blog of Instantbird's development - nightly</title><link>http://blog.instantbird.org/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2014 13:07:07 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Linux nightly builds back!</title><link>http://blog.instantbird.org/2014/07/linux-nightly-builds-back/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Back in March, we posted that we had started
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blog.instantbird.org/articles/pardon-the-interruption-instantbird-nightly-builds-are-back.rst"&gt;building nightly builds from mozilla-central/comm-central&lt;/a&gt;, but because the
version of CentOS we had been using was too old, we were unable to continue
providing Linux nightly builds. That has now changed and (as of today) we have
&lt;strong&gt;both 32-bit and 64-bit&lt;/strong&gt; Linux nightlies! Since this involved us installing a
new operating system (CentOS 6.2) and tweaking some of the build configuration
for Linux, please &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/enter_bug.cgi?product=Instantbird"&gt;let us know&lt;/a&gt; if you see any issues! Additionally, some more
up-to-date features that have been available in Mozilla Firefox for a while
should now be available in Instantbird (e.g. dbus and pulse audio support) and
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=955310"&gt;even some minor bugs were fixed&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sorry that this took so long, but &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ftp.instantbird.com/instantbird/nightly/latest-trunk/"&gt;go grab your updated copy now&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">clokep</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2014 13:07:07 +0000</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.instantbird.org,2014-07-25:/2014/07/linux-nightly-builds-back/</guid><category>Development</category><category>nightly</category><category>status update</category></item><item><title>Pardon the Interruption! Instantbird nightly builds are back!</title><link>http://blog.instantbird.org/2014/03/pardon-the-interruption-instantbird-nightly-builds-are-back/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;As of today, March 3rd, 2014, Instantbird nightly builds (1.6a1pre) are being
built again. We last had nightly builds on January 9th, 2014 and they have been
broken since due to a series of a large infrastructure change we’ve been going
through to merge the Instantbird Bugzilla and code repository with Mozilla’s.
Unfortunately, getting nightly builds working again took us longer than expected
as it involved many related issues: updating Instantbird to work with newer
versions of Mozilla, reconfiguring our buildbot and working on getting libpurple
to build as an&amp;nbsp;extension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results of this is that Instantbird is now building out of the
“comm-central” code repository (the same place the code for Thunderbird is
stored). What does this mean for&amp;nbsp;you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Instantbird nightlies are now built using comm-central/mozilla-central: bugs
fixed in Mozilla will be reflected in the next Instantbird&amp;nbsp;nightly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Instantbird 1.6a1pre is currently based on Mozilla 30, this is a bit of a
jump from Instantbird 1.5 (Mozilla 25). There might be an influx of bugs as
any issues caused by this jump are worked out. Please report any issues you&amp;nbsp;see!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Not entirely related) Bugs for Instantbird can now be reported on
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/"&gt;bugzilla.mozilla.org&lt;/a&gt; under the “Instantbird” and “Chat Core” (for bugs
shared with Thunderbird Chat)&amp;nbsp;products.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Current nightly builds are located at on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ftp.instantbird.com/instantbird/nightly/latest-1.6a1pre/"&gt;our ftp site&lt;/a&gt;, but automatic
updating from older nightlies should still&amp;nbsp;work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, sorry for any interruption. Regular development should be continuing now. Thanks for all the concerned emails telling us our builds had&amp;nbsp;stopped!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">clokep</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2014 12:21:35 +0000</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.instantbird.org,2014-03-03:/2014/03/pardon-the-interruption-instantbird-nightly-builds-are-back/</guid><category>Development</category><category>mozilla</category><category>nightly</category><category>status update</category></item><item><title>Nightlies fixed and with upgraded libpurple</title><link>http://blog.instantbird.org/2010/09/nightlies-fixed-and-with-upgraded-libpurple/</link><description>&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have nightly builds again on all 3 OSes.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have had issues on the physical machine that hosts our Windows
and Linux compilation virtual machines. &lt;em&gt;Even&lt;/em&gt; has been hard at
work to get them back online as quickly as&amp;nbsp;possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Additionally, our Windows builds failed with the obscure
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;gklayout.lib&amp;nbsp;: fatal error &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LNK1106&lt;/span&gt;: invalid file or disk full: cannot seek to 0x2000D93C&lt;/tt&gt;
error message. No, the disk wasn&amp;#8217;t full, that would be too easy to
understand&amp;#8230; After a lot of wasted effort trying to figure out
what had changed in the configuration of that machine or in the
code, we finally got the solution on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRC&lt;/span&gt; from &lt;em&gt;khuey&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;ted&lt;/em&gt;
(thanks!): reboot with the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;/&lt;span class="caps"&gt;3GB&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; switch to extend the address&amp;nbsp;space.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The add-ons manager is usable again on nightlies. We got tired of
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=591801"&gt;bug 591801&lt;/a&gt;
and pushed for Instantbird a partial backout of the patch from &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=562797"&gt;bug
562797&lt;/a&gt;. (I
haven&amp;#8217;t attached it in the bug because this is clearly not a fix, but
if other xulrunner application developers want to use it, it&amp;#8217;s
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://hg.instantbird.org/instantbird/file/97e5db711d11/tools/patches/partial-backout-bug-562797.patch"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
I know Daniel was very happy to have it for
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bluegriffon.org/"&gt;BlueGriffon&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Known issue: Message Styles currently don&amp;#8217;t work without &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blog.mozilla.com/addons/2010/09/23/changes-to-how-extensions-are-installed-in-firefox-4/"&gt;being
unpacked in the profile
folder&lt;/a&gt;.
This means that even though the add-on manager now works, if you
install Message Styles with it in your new nightly, they won&amp;#8217;t work.
Message Styles that were already installed will continue to work even
if you upgrade your&amp;nbsp;nightly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have upgraded libpurple from version 2.6.6 to 2.7.3:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No big disaster has been reported, so nightly testers probably
don&amp;#8217;t need to fear the&amp;nbsp;update.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are tracking the crash reports: we have seen some new reports
related to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MSN&lt;/span&gt; protocol; we will investigate&amp;nbsp;soon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Gadu-Gadu protocol support has improved, but is not as fixed
as we hoped it would be. We will see if we can find ways to fix&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our translators may be interested in taking strings from
translation files generated based on this new version to help them
in the process of upgrading their locale. These new converted
files are available
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://queze.net/goinfre/l10n/libpurple-2.7.3/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The patches for minor issues that had been waiting in bugzilla for
quite a bit of time (because we didn&amp;#8217;t want to land them just before
releasing 0.2 or in the middle of the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;js-proto&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;mozilla2&lt;/tt&gt;
branch merges) have&amp;nbsp;landed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have welcomed translators for two new locales: Chinese and Hebrew!
&lt;img alt=":)" src="http://blog.instantbird.org/smileys/sourire.png" /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have created an &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;experiments&lt;/tt&gt; mercurial repository where
contributors from our community are enthusiastically experimenting
with projects that we look forward to integrating in the default
Instantbird code base once they are ready:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mic&lt;/em&gt; is working on adapting Firefox Sync to work with&amp;nbsp;Instantbird.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;clokep&lt;/em&gt; is working on a readable implementation of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRC&lt;/span&gt;
protocols in JavaScript, leveraging the work that has been done in
the last few months on the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;js-proto&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; branch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I plan to start rewriting the backend of our buddy list next week.
The goals of this work are to simplify the code, make it work
correctly with protocol plugins implemented in JavaScript, and give
us the necessary APIs to implement the contact and tag features we
plan add for the 0.3&amp;nbsp;release.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, don&amp;#8217;t hesitate to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugzilla.instantbird.org/enter_bug.cgi"&gt;file
bugs&lt;/a&gt; if you come
across them! You are also welcome to join us on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRC&lt;/span&gt; (in
&lt;a class="reference external" href="irc://irc.mozilla.org/#instantbird"&gt;#instantbird&lt;/a&gt;, where we have
been more than 20 a few times this&amp;nbsp;week!)&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">flo</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 24 Sep 2010 19:35:54 +0000</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.instantbird.org,2010-09-24:/2010/09/nightlies-fixed-and-with-upgraded-libpurple/</guid><category>Development</category><category>libpurple</category><category>nightly</category></item><item><title>Nightly builds now based on mozilla-central</title><link>http://blog.instantbird.org/2010/09/nightly-builds-now-based-on-mozilla-central/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In late July, I started working on making Instantbird use the Mozilla
2.0 platform (which the recently released Firefox 4 betas are based on).
This work, which started in a branch, has recently reached a point where
we believe it could benefit from wider testing. The &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;mozilla2&lt;/tt&gt; branch
was merged Friday, September 10th,&amp;nbsp;2010.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This didn&amp;#8217;t happen as smoothly as I would have hoped, but after 10 (!)
bustage fixes, yesterday we were able to provide the first set of
Instantbird nightly builds based on Mozilla 2.0. Our slowly growing
community on &lt;a class="reference external" href="irc://irc.mozilla.org/#instantbird"&gt;#instantbird&lt;/a&gt; has
jumped on them, and quickly reported a few significant issues. Thanks to
their awesome help, those are fixed, and today we have a new set of
nightly&amp;nbsp;builds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additional help to test these new builds (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ftp.instantbird.com/instantbird/nightly/2010/09/2010-09-13-04-instantbird/"&gt;Windows and
Linux&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ftp.instantbird.com/instantbird/nightly/2010/09/2010-09-13-09-instantbird/"&gt;Mac&lt;/a&gt;),
will be greatly&amp;nbsp;appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Known issues of this set of&amp;nbsp;builds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &amp;#8216;Show Logs&amp;#8217; menuitems don&amp;#8217;t work (already fixed and will work&amp;nbsp;tomorrow).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Add-ons manager is broken. This is &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=591801"&gt;bug
591801&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &amp;#8216;Instantbird&amp;#8217; checkbox in the &amp;#8216;Update&amp;#8217; pane of the &amp;#8216;Advanced&amp;#8217;
panel of the preference Window is disabled (already fixed and will
work&amp;nbsp;tomorrow).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">flo</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 13 Sep 2010 16:24:07 +0000</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.instantbird.org,2010-09-13:/2010/09/nightly-builds-now-based-on-mozilla-central/</guid><category>Development</category><category>mozilla</category><category>nightly</category></item><item><title>Nightly builds available</title><link>http://blog.instantbird.org/2008/10/nightly-builds-available/</link><description>&lt;div class="section" id="nightly-builds"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Nightly&amp;nbsp;builds&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We produce nightly builds of Instantbird every day with buildbot. These
builds can be downloaded from our server at
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ftp.instantbird.com/instantbird/nightly/latest-trunk/"&gt;http://ftp.instantbird.com/instantbird/nightly/latest-trunk/&lt;/a&gt;. Please
note that these builds are available for testing purpose only, and are
totally untested before we put them online. Use them at your own risks.
If you want to help us with testing, there is no need to download and
install a new build from the server everyday, the application will
automatically propose&amp;nbsp;updates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To ensure that users won&amp;#8217;t confuse nightly unstable builds with
releases, we use a different set of icons for the nightlies. The nightly
icon&amp;nbsp;is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Nightly logo" src="http://www.instantbird.com/images/nightly.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="what-s-new"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;new?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has already been a few months since the last release, so I guess it&amp;#8217;s
a good time for a quick status&amp;nbsp;update.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just after the 0.1.2 release, we switched from subversion to mercurial
for the versioning of our source code. Our mercurial repository is
publicly available at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://hg.instantbird.org/"&gt;http://hg.instantbird.org/&lt;/a&gt;. At the same time, for
the Mozilla code we use, we switched from the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CVS&lt;/span&gt; trunk (1.9.0.x) to
mozilla-central and we are now using a build system which is very
similar to the comm-central one. In fact, it&amp;#8217;s a copy of it with very
small modifications. Thanks to the people who helped us for the
transition and to the people who worked on the comm-central build&amp;nbsp;system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also some new features: There&amp;#8217;s a findbar in the conversation
window (Ctrl/Cmd + F to open it), commands (/me, /topic, etc&amp;#8230;) work in
conversations, the list of chat room participants is displayed (for
example, in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRC&lt;/span&gt; channels), typing notifications work, idleness (becoming
idle based on the inactivity time) works, status changes are displayed
in conversations, it&amp;#8217;s possible to force a check for update,&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also spent time on code cleanup (debug logging for example) and
stability improvements (taking into account the data from the crash
reporting&amp;nbsp;system).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="what-s-next"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;next?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We plan to do another minor release soon, and after that, for the 0.2
release, the focus will be on&amp;nbsp;extensibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a side note, this project has been public for one year, Instantbird
0.1 was released on October 18th, 2007. Even if we hoped to do more,
it&amp;#8217;s been a great year for the&amp;nbsp;project!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">flo</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2008 16:23:43 +0000</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.instantbird.org,2008-10-18:/2008/10/nightly-builds-available/</guid><category>Downloads</category><category>nightly</category></item></channel></rss>