<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The blog of Instantbird's development - Comments: Introducing Time Bubbles</title><link href="http://blog.instantbird.org/2011/06/introducing-time-bubbles//" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://blog.instantbird.org/feeds/comment.introducing-time-bubbles.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://blog.instantbird.org/2011/06/introducing-time-bubbles//</id><updated>2011-06-19T00:34:00+00:00</updated><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title>Posted by: Florian</title><link href="http://blog.instantbird.org/2011/06/introducing-time-bubbles/#comment-198" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-06-19T00:34:00+00:00</published><updated>2011-06-19T00:34:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian</name></author><id>tag:blog.instantbird.org,2011-06-19:/2011/06/introducing-time-bubbles//comment-198</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;#64;Scarrer&lt;/strong&gt;: Don&amp;#8217;t the messages that scroll away (quite fast in the first seconds, and slower after because of the logarithmic scale) give a more accurate perception of silence than timestamps can do? Anyway, if you feel you have a very specific use case that diverges from what a typical …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;#64;Scarrer&lt;/strong&gt;: Don&amp;#8217;t the messages that scroll away (quite fast in the first seconds, and slower after because of the logarithmic scale) give a more accurate perception of silence than timestamps can do? Anyway, if you feel you have a very specific use case that diverges from what a typical chat may be, it&amp;#8217;s totally &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt; to customize your instant messenger for that specific use case :). We have 4 different message themes included by default (look in the preferences dialog), and lots more to download from the add-ons&amp;nbsp;website.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Posted by: Scarrer</title><link href="http://blog.instantbird.org/2011/06/introducing-time-bubbles/#comment-197" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-06-19T00:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2011-06-19T00:09:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Scarrer</name></author><id>tag:blog.instantbird.org,2011-06-19:/2011/06/introducing-time-bubbles//comment-197</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve no stats on this but the number &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; size of support groups such as National Self Harm Network imply that some significant proportion of I.M users will be having intense chats. In these sorts of chats your eye is literally on the clock &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; the time stamps to keep …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve no stats on this but the number &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; size of support groups such as National Self Harm Network imply that some significant proportion of I.M users will be having intense chats. In these sorts of chats your eye is literally on the clock &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; the time stamps to keep the responses close enough that the person on the other end hasn&amp;#8217;t time to do anything drastic or else to know that the silence has passed a critical benchmark (say how long a tourniquet has been on or an O/D taken. Admittedly these aren&amp;#8217;t your typical chats but I suspect there are enough such out there to make a category that genuinely needs second by second time in the&amp;nbsp;chats.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Posted by: Florian</title><link href="http://blog.instantbird.org/2011/06/introducing-time-bubbles/#comment-195" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-06-13T18:44:00+00:00</published><updated>2011-06-13T18:44:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian</name></author><id>tag:blog.instantbird.org,2011-06-13:/2011/06/introducing-time-bubbles//comment-195</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;#64;Mads&lt;/strong&gt;: I think you are likely to really like the &amp;#8216;Paper Sheets&amp;#8217; theme (also installed by default): it shows the time stamp right-aligned, in gray for the first message of a group and light gray for the next messages (which turns to normal gray when hovering for better&amp;nbsp;readability).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;#64;Mads&lt;/strong&gt;: I think you are likely to really like the &amp;#8216;Paper Sheets&amp;#8217; theme (also installed by default): it shows the time stamp right-aligned, in gray for the first message of a group and light gray for the next messages (which turns to normal gray when hovering for better&amp;nbsp;readability).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For your suggestion of showing the time on the same line as the username in the &amp;#8216;Bubbles&amp;#8217; theme, I think you missed the fact that we display the username only for the first message of a&amp;nbsp;group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I certainly disagree with your feeling that &amp;#8220;users have to work harder&amp;#8221; when provided with the direct answer to their question, rather than having to read and compute the answer using a numeric representation of the time. I think I explained this in the post already&amp;nbsp;:).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, thanks for your&amp;nbsp;feedback!&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Posted by: Mads</title><link href="http://blog.instantbird.org/2011/06/introducing-time-bubbles/#comment-194" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-06-12T18:33:00+00:00</published><updated>2011-06-12T18:33:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Mads</name></author><id>tag:blog.instantbird.org,2011-06-12:/2011/06/introducing-time-bubbles//comment-194</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you add the timestamp next to the username you are not taking up additional space and people can easily get the time of whatever message they need the time of, instead of constantly guessing. For example, the iPhone has a similar system to time stamping messages, but to normal …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you add the timestamp next to the username you are not taking up additional space and people can easily get the time of whatever message they need the time of, instead of constantly guessing. For example, the iPhone has a similar system to time stamping messages, but to normal users the timestamps appear to be added randomly. Moreover, users don&amp;#8217;t know the logic behind this complex timestamping scheme and are left to guess when estimating the timestamp of that one particularly message they&amp;#8217;d like to know the time&amp;nbsp;of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just show the timestamp right-aligned on the same line as the username, but in a color less strong. Having users guess how to access the timestamp seems counterproductive. You have to code more, users have to work harder, just to show basic&amp;nbsp;information.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Posted by: Neil</title><link href="http://blog.instantbird.org/2011/06/introducing-time-bubbles/#comment-193" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-06-09T09:44:00+00:00</published><updated>2011-06-09T09:44:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Neil</name></author><id>tag:blog.instantbird.org,2011-06-09:/2011/06/introducing-time-bubbles//comment-193</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This looks fantastic, excellent work Florian! It&amp;#8217;s great to see so much thought has been put into something that seems simple at first&amp;nbsp;glance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t think that making the user responsible for choosing between two not-so-good options which one is best is a good way to address …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This looks fantastic, excellent work Florian! It&amp;#8217;s great to see so much thought has been put into something that seems simple at first&amp;nbsp;glance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t think that making the user responsible for choosing between two not-so-good options which one is best is a good way to address this&amp;nbsp;issue.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Couldn&amp;#8217;t agree more, I&amp;#8217;m so glad Instantbird is being developed with this sort of philosophy; when you look at clients like Miranda and they just cram in a million different options for a million different tastes and preferences, it&amp;#8217;s just embarrassing&amp;nbsp;:-)&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry></feed>