<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The blog of Instantbird's development - Comments: Better contact list</title><link href="http://blog.instantbird.org/2011/06/better-contact-list//" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://blog.instantbird.org/feeds/comment.better-contact-list.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://blog.instantbird.org/2011/06/better-contact-list//</id><updated>2012-01-04T21:17:00+00:00</updated><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title>Posted by: Johnathan</title><link href="http://blog.instantbird.org/2011/06/better-contact-list/#comment-1159" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-01-04T21:17:00+00:00</published><updated>2012-01-04T21:17:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Johnathan</name></author><id>tag:blog.instantbird.org,2012-01-04:/2011/06/better-contact-list//comment-1159</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Is there a way to massively move contacts from one tag to another&amp;#8230; or maybe renaming a tag group from one name to another or to an existing tag group to combine&amp;nbsp;them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a ton of contacts and want to move multiple folks from under one tag to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Is there a way to massively move contacts from one tag to another&amp;#8230; or maybe renaming a tag group from one name to another or to an existing tag group to combine&amp;nbsp;them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a ton of contacts and want to move multiple folks from under one tag to another, A way to do this would be greatly&amp;nbsp;appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Posted by: Florian</title><link href="http://blog.instantbird.org/2011/06/better-contact-list/#comment-249" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-07-10T00:15:00+00:00</published><updated>2011-07-10T00:15:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian</name></author><id>tag:blog.instantbird.org,2011-07-10:/2011/06/better-contact-list//comment-249</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Maybe you have used Pidgin for years?&amp;nbsp;;)&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Posted by: patrickjdempsey</title><link href="http://blog.instantbird.org/2011/06/better-contact-list/#comment-248" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-07-10T00:07:00+00:00</published><updated>2011-07-10T00:07:00+00:00</updated><author><name>patrickjdempsey</name></author><id>tag:blog.instantbird.org,2011-07-10:/2011/06/better-contact-list//comment-248</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;You know what Florian&amp;#8230; you are right.. I have no idea why I though you could&amp;nbsp;before!&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Posted by: Florian</title><link href="http://blog.instantbird.org/2011/06/better-contact-list/#comment-247" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-07-09T20:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2011-07-09T20:09:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian</name></author><id>tag:blog.instantbird.org,2011-07-09:/2011/06/better-contact-list//comment-247</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;#64;patrickjdempsey&lt;/strong&gt;: Thanks for the feedback! I&amp;#8217;m not aware of a meta bug for the buddy list, feel free to create one if you feel the need&amp;nbsp;:).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: we have never supported moving a buddy from a group into another by a drag and drop in the&amp;nbsp;past.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Posted by: patrickjdempsey</title><link href="http://blog.instantbird.org/2011/06/better-contact-list/#comment-246" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-07-09T20:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2011-07-09T20:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>patrickjdempsey</name></author><id>tag:blog.instantbird.org,2011-07-09:/2011/06/better-contact-list//comment-246</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Also, is there a meta bug on improving the buddy list I can add some bugs&amp;nbsp;to?&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Posted by: patrickjdempsey</title><link href="http://blog.instantbird.org/2011/06/better-contact-list/#comment-245" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-07-09T19:44:00+00:00</published><updated>2011-07-09T19:44:00+00:00</updated><author><name>patrickjdempsey</name></author><id>tag:blog.instantbird.org,2011-07-09:/2011/06/better-contact-list//comment-245</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ok, I&amp;#8217;m seeing now that I can collapse the tags without closing them&amp;#8230; that really confused me when I hit the X button and the contacts moved&amp;nbsp;around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dragging thing is really confusing for me. In every &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UI&lt;/span&gt; I&amp;#8217;ve ever used dragging an item from one place …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ok, I&amp;#8217;m seeing now that I can collapse the tags without closing them&amp;#8230; that really confused me when I hit the X button and the contacts moved&amp;nbsp;around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dragging thing is really confusing for me. In every &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UI&lt;/span&gt; I&amp;#8217;ve ever used dragging an item from one place to another place physically moves it. In this new system dragging items does not move them as I would expect. In fact, a whole series of unexpected things happen when you drag a buddy. Instead of an item disappearing from one list and appearing on another like in the old system, the item disappears altogether and it&amp;#8217;s old position is renamed to the new buddy name it&amp;#8217;s been merged with. That&amp;#8217;s two really unexpected actions at once. And it&amp;#8217;s not easy to figure out how to correct that. Context menus are almost never intuitive! I feel like you&amp;#8217;ve hidden all of the important &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UI&lt;/span&gt; interaction behind context menus and made the upfront &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UI&lt;/span&gt; difficult to understand. There&amp;#8217;s also a bug where sometimes contacts get renamed to the name of the buddy they are merged with that makes it even more confusing! I notice you do have the note &amp;#8220;drop a contact her to merge it&amp;#8221; but this only appears in an expanded contact list, which most users will not notice at first. These are some suggestions I have after playing around with the new&amp;nbsp;system:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hide the buddy information popups when an item is &amp;#8220;grabbed&amp;#8221; with the mouse, as they get in the&amp;nbsp;way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Offer a way to organize buddies by dragging without using the context menus: dragging a buddy into the name of the tag should *move* it into that tag group. (And I mean move, not copy! remove from previous group and add to new group). This would also allow a way to remove a buddy from one tag without using the context menu, as well as allow a way to remove a buddy from the contact list it&amp;#8217;s in by dragging it to group name. That is the kind of interaction most people familiar with mouse-based &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UI&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s will expect I&amp;nbsp;think.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Show instructional popups while buddies are being dragged: &amp;#8220;Move to this tag group&amp;#8221; &amp;#8220;Merge into this contact&amp;nbsp;list&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automatically show the full contact list when a buddy is merged into that list via the mouse. This will avoid that &amp;#8220;where did it go????&amp;#8221; syndrome. It will also make it easier to find and visually confirm if you accidentally drop a buddy in the wrong contact list. Currently accidentally dropping a buddy means it&amp;#8217;s basically lost until you go through all of the contacts and expand them one by&amp;nbsp;one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dispense with the collapsing of the contact list. Clicking on a buddy should show all of the information the first time without multiple clicks. This will also help to avoid &amp;#8220;loosing&amp;#8221; buddies if you accidentally drop them into a contact&amp;nbsp;list.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When clicking on one buddy from another, perhaps the collapsing of the old buddy info and the expanding of the new buddy info should be animated? Especially with the expanded contact lists there gets to be a jumpy interaction where the mouse isn&amp;#8217;t sitting on the same spot in the list where it was&amp;nbsp;before.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dispense with the redundant name in the contact&amp;nbsp;list.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Offer an X button beside buddies in a contact list to remove them from the&amp;nbsp;list.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Offer a &amp;#8220;chat&amp;#8221; button beside buddies in a contact list on hover. If the chat button is offered on the top level of the contact list, why isn&amp;#8217;t it offered inside the&amp;nbsp;list?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visual clue that a buddy name contains a hidden contact list. I&amp;#8217;m not a fan of visual clutter, but I think it&amp;#8217;s important to show a distinction between a single buddy and a hidden contact list. It could be something simple like having the text in&amp;nbsp;bold?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Posted by: Florian</title><link href="http://blog.instantbird.org/2011/06/better-contact-list/#comment-238" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-07-08T11:43:00+00:00</published><updated>2011-07-08T11:43:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian</name></author><id>tag:blog.instantbird.org,2011-07-08:/2011/06/better-contact-list//comment-238</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;#64;patrickjdempsey&lt;/strong&gt; I have about 20 accounts, some of which I&amp;#8217;ve had for about 10 years too, and thousands of buddies, so I don&amp;#8217;t think this point is relevant&amp;nbsp;here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;if you drag buddies around you end up with more and more copies of them all over the place …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;#64;patrickjdempsey&lt;/strong&gt; I have about 20 accounts, some of which I&amp;#8217;ve had for about 10 years too, and thousands of buddies, so I don&amp;#8217;t think this point is relevant&amp;nbsp;here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;if you drag buddies around you end up with more and more copies of them all over the place&amp;#8221; this sentence makes no sense to me. Drag and drop is used to merge buddies into contacts, it&amp;#8217;s not related to tags or groups (and a contact has all the tags of the buddies that compose it, but it doesn&amp;#8217;t add&amp;nbsp;more).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;when you &amp;#8220;close&amp;#8221; a tag it just moves all of the untagged buddies down to the bottom instead of hiding them.&amp;#8221; I don&amp;#8217;t understand this either. Or are you maybe confusing closing and hiding a tag? To close a tag, double click on its name or click on the icon at the left of the name. Closing a tag is useful for people you want to have in a separate place, but don&amp;#8217;t need to interact with at the moment. Hiding a tag is a completely different operation (done with the [X] icon at the right of the tag name, or from the context menu) to ignore tags that are totally meaningless without having to remove the tag from each of the contained&amp;nbsp;contacts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this clarifies things, if it doesn&amp;#8217;t, please do get back to me as I would like to understand your problem if there is one beside the apparent confusion. In any case, thanks for your feedback!&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry></feed>